<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reason against rage being some animadversions upon a late scurrilous libel, prefix'd to a sermon preach'd nine and thirty years ago; and dedicated in these words, (viz.) to Mr. Serj. Powlett, recorder of the City of Bristol, and Mr. Robert Yate, mercht. Together with an occasional discussion of some particulars relating to persecution, and liberty of conscience. To which is subjoyn'd, a brief application, made by way of advice, humbly offered to all the inhabitants of the City aforesaid. By Thomas Speed.</title>
            <author>Speed, Thomas, b. 1622 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61076)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2135:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reason against rage being some animadversions upon a late scurrilous libel, prefix'd to a sermon preach'd nine and thirty years ago; and dedicated in these words, (viz.) to Mr. Serj. Powlett, recorder of the City of Bristol, and Mr. Robert Yate, mercht. Together with an occasional discussion of some particulars relating to persecution, and liberty of conscience. To which is subjoyn'd, a brief application, made by way of advice, humbly offered to all the inhabitants of the City aforesaid. By Thomas Speed.</title>
                  <author>Speed, Thomas, b. 1622 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Northcott, in George-Yard in Lombard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36621:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon againſt Rage:</hi> Being Some ANIMADVERSIONS UPON A late Scurrilous LIBEL, Prefix'd to A SERMON Preach'd Nine and thirty Years ago; And Dedicated in theſe Words, <hi>(VIZ.) To Mr. Serj.</hi> Powlett, <hi>Recorder of the City of</hi> Briſtol, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Robert Yate, <hi>Merch<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER With an Occaſional Diſcuſſion of ſome Particulars rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is ſubjoyn'd, A brief Application, made by way of Advice, humbly offered to all the Inhabitants of the City aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS SPEED.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeemeth juſt, but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Knowing this firſt, that there ſhall come in the laſt days ſcoffers, walking after their own luſts,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Pet. 3.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Nihil magis praeſtandum eſt, quàm ne, pecorum ritu, ſequamur antecedentium gregem, pergentes non quò eundum est, ſed quò itur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Seneca de vit. Beat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Northcott,</hi> in <hi>George-Yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36621:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36621:2"/>
            <head>To the Honeſt-hearted Impartial READER.</head>
            <p>HAd not my Indiſpoſition, through Age, together with ſome emergent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions prevented it, I had ſooner appeared to obviate the Envy of my cauſleſs Adverſaries, and to diſperſe thoſe Fogs of falſe Suggeſtions, by which they have craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily endeavoured to cast a Mist before the Eyes of their well-meaning, but unwary Readers. Read what I have written with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, and (having begun) let me deſire thee, to beſtow a little time out of thy vacant Hours, to read it throughout, lest by a tranſient taking up a Sentence here, and a Sentence there, thou ſhouldest happen (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendedly) to do me, or my Adverſaries, wrong, for want of a full, and a ſedate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of Things, with Things, and Times, with Times, relating to the Matters in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt us.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36621:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36621:3"/>
            <head>Reaſon againſt Rage.</head>
            <p>I Once thought that I might have paſs'd the remainder of my Life in ſilence, and not have had occaſion to appear to the World in Print; but that meeting lately with a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Libel, contriv'd, and publiſh'd (on occaſion of the late Election of Members of Parliament for the City of <hi>Briſtol</hi>) on purpoſe to expoſe, and (if poſſible) to draw into popular contempt, the two Candidates, my ſelf, and other the ſober Citizens that gave their Votes for them, I thought my ſelf obliged to appear in Print for the clearing of the Innocent, the fixing the evil upon the Evil-doer, and the undeceiving of all thoſe well-meaning Citizens, who, through too much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, may, without due examination had of men and things, conceive an inward diſpleaſure againſt ſuch as have not deſerv'd it.</p>
            <p>In all caſes, where a man is accuſed as a criminal, it's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judg'd both juſt, and reaſonable, that he ſhould know both his Crime, and his Accuſers.</p>
            <p>My Crime is not expreſly mentioned in the venemous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, but is therein ſo plainly implied, that I am fully ſatisfied what it is; but the Names of my Accuſers I muſt not know, being hid under the Letters,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.D. N.K. J.E. S.W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why ſo? Were you aſhamed to own that in publick under your Names, which you had maliciouſly framed in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate? You know it's an old received Maxim, (<note n="*" place="margin">Veritas non quaerit angulos.</note> 
               <hi>Truth ſeeks not corners,</hi>) but is bold and bare-faced: He that hath Truth on his ſide, need not be aſhamed to own it. Poſſibly when you ſeriouſly had reflected on what ye had written, you thought it unbecoming any ingenuous and ſober-minded men (as well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36621:4"/>you might) publickly to be known to be the Authors of ſo deformed a Libel, whoſe Contents are fitter to be turn'd into a Song, to be ſung by a Crew of Drunkards at an Ale-bench, than to be expoſed to the view and peruſal of any judicious and ſerious Readers. And therefore I ſhall be content at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that your review of the foulneſs of the birth of your own begetting, may paſs as an Apology, for the concealment of your Names.</p>
            <p>But, Sirs, although you have kept me ignorant of your Names, by your Expreſſions I clearly diſcern your Spirits. (<note n="*" place="margin">Exungue Leonem.</note> The Lion cannot be hid where his Claw is ſeen.) And therefore be not offended, if I deal plainly with you, (for flatter you I dare not) and tell you, that that Spirit which writ that ſcoffing Paper, and reprinted that Sermon, thirſteth after Blood, and would rejoyce to have mine, and the Lives of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the peaceable Diſſenters in the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> be offer'd up as a ſacrifice to your implacable envy and revenge.</p>
            <p>'Tis the ſame Spirit of Perſecution, that, but a few Years paſs'd, drove many religious worſhippers of God, according to their ſeveral perſwaſions, into corners, whileſt Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Prophaneneſs walk'd to and fro in the open Streets, without controul. What levying of Fines was there? What ſpoiling peaceable Neighbours of their Goods? What ſierce Proſecutions of them by Indictments in Courts of Juſtice? How zealouſly active were they, who were poſſeſs'd with this Spirit, in roving, running, and hunting after religious Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? ſearching Houſes, prying into all Creeks and Corners, (but ſuſpected for that Exerciſe) haling ſuch as they found (if above ſuch a number) either praying to Almighty God, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly diſcourſing about their Souls concerns, before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, as if there had been then no other crime more hainous, and more deſerving to be puniſhed by Authority, than Peoples worſhipping the God that made them, in that manner which they believed was moſt acceptable to him.</p>
            <p>And more particularly, 'twas this Spirit that then hurried many innocent and peaceable Inhabitants of this City (without any regard to Age or Sex) into the noyſom Goal of <hi>Newgate,</hi> where they were treated by thoſe that caſt them in, more like Dogs, than like Chriſtian Men and Women. What generous ſpirited perſon is there, who (delighting in Dogs) would not,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36621:4"/>in caſe of any of their ſickneſs, not only allow, but command their Keeper, to let them out of their Kennel into the open Air, in order to their recovery? But this benefit was denied to the languiſhing bodies of ſeveral of theſe innocent ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who lay throng'd together in that miſerable manner, in that unwholſom Priſon, ready to be ſtifled for want of Air to breath in, and convenient room for Reſt, that the ſenſe of their ſad condition would have drawn tears from hearts of Flint.</p>
            <p>Their Complaints were ſpread abroad in the City, and the Cry of their Barbarous Uſage was great. Which, though it had no influence on their Perſecutors to move them to pity, yet it begot ſo much compaſſion in the hearts of ſome ſober Citizens (all or moſt of whom are yet living) as that they went to view the Priſon, and inquire into the diſtreſſed condition of their ſuffering Neighbours, who (upon ſtrict obſervation made touching both,) did (like merciful men) give the following Certificate under their Hands, <hi>(viz.) We find the ſaid Goal is very noiſom in general, and void of out-let for Air, and therefore unfit to contain ſo great a number of Priſoners as we now find therein, being One hundred twenty and five cloſe Priſoners, beſides the Keeper and his Family, Fourſcore and five whereof are the People called</hi> Quakers, <hi>who are unreaſonably throng'd together, filling all the Rooms in the Goal, fit for lodging, (except where the Felons are) with four, five, ſix, ſeven, and nine Beds in a Room, beſides divers little corners filled with three in a Bed. Notwithſtanding all which, many of theſe People are neceſſitated to lye on the ground, and ſpreading their Mats on the ground, they lye at a miſerable rate, that it was a grief to us to behold,</hi> (viz.) <hi>ſome athwart the Room, ſome under the Table, (being a Kennel where the Dogs were wont to lye) ſome upon the Tables, and ſome in Hammocks over the Table, which neceſſarily endangers their lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Certificate of the like Contents was given in, under the Hands of four publickly known Phyſicians, inhabitants of the City (who are yet living) who ſay, among other things, <hi>That great numbers of the People called</hi> Quakers, <hi>were throng'd in a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable manner, into the noiſom Goal of</hi> Newgate, <hi>and are deſtitute of room for reſt, which hath a ready tendency to the deſtroying them, and to the indangering of the lives, not only of the ſaid Priſoners, but of the many Inhabitants of this great and populous City.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36621:5"/>
            <p> Notwithſtanding which, the Bonds of the Priſoners were not looſed, nor the Priſon doors opened, that the ſick might have the benefit of the open air to breath in, in order to their recovery, although large ſecurity was tendred for their return again into Priſon, either alive, if recovered, or their Bodies in caſe of death; but this was rejected: ſo that they were ſtill continued under their mercileſs confinement and cruel uſage (the particulars of which I ſhall forbear to mention) until it pleaſed the Lord to deliver five of them from the hands of their oppreſſors, by death in the Priſon; and a ſixth, that was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of the Priſon (but too late) ſoon died, and was return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back, and buried thence.</p>
            <p>Upon one of which ſix (being a woman of known honeſty and of good reputation in the City) was exerciſed a piece of cruelty exceeding (if poſſible) that of Pagans; who, after ſhe had long languiſh'd under the ſeverities of the Goal, being at the point of death, deſired the company of ſome of her Friends and fellow Priſoners, with whom ſhe would have had ſome converſe, before her departure out of the world, a thing grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Traytors and Felons before their Execution, but was denied to this dying woman; and inſtead thereof, many of her friends, ſhe deſired might come to her, were barbarouſly lockt up in their reſpective Rooms and Holes, to prevent their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the requeſt of their dying Friend.</p>
            <p>With what aſtoniſhment will the next Proteſtant Age be ſurprized! When as they ſhall find upon record ſuch Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties exerciſed by Chriſtians upon Chriſtians, and by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants upon Proteſtants: eſpecially when by inquiry they ſhall be ſatisfied, that the crimes charg'd againſt the ſufferers were of no deeper dye, than the peaceable exerciſe of their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces towards God, and their worſhipping him in that way which they did believe to be moſt acceptable to him, without doing the leaſt civil injury to their Neighbour.</p>
            <p>I mention not theſe Cruelties (God is my witneſs) with the leaſt deſire or deſign to provoke the living ſufferers to ſo much as a thought of revenge, or maliciouſly to expoſe the perſons of their oppreſſors: No, far be it from me; I hope there is not one of thoſe, that patiently bore the fierce heat of that day of their Afflictors wrath, but what hath ſo well learned the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrin, as to be able truly to ſay, with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36621:5"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>Being reviled we bleſs, being perſecnted we ſuffer it.</hi> And I doubt not, but that had they who died in the Priſon been ask'd one by one at their dying hour, what revenge they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire upon thoſe, through whoſe ſeverities they were then drawing their laſt breath, they would heartily have cryed out with that holy Martyr <hi>Stephen,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 7.60.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge.</hi> It's for the ſake of thoſe, that are yet living, who were either Actors or Abettors of any of theſe Diſmal Tragedies, that I mention theſe things, for whom I do make it my hearty ſupplication unto the God of all Mercies, that he would ſhew them mercy, in giving them a true ſight and ſenſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian practices, before they go off the ſtage of this World, that they may with contrite hearts turn to the Lord their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker (againſt whom they have been ſtriving) before they go down to their Graves, in which there will be found no place for repentance.</p>
            <p>It will not avail the guilty, in the day of God's righteous judgment, to plead for their juſtification, that they had a Law, and by that Law they made havoke of the Goods, cruelly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned the Perſons, and brought ſore Diſtreſs upon the Families of their diſſenting (but peaceable-living) Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, againſt whom they could find no occaſion, but (as they of old againſt <hi>Daniel</hi>)<note n="‖" place="margin">Dan. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>concerning the Law of their God.</hi> This was the laſt and ſtrongeſt Plea, that the Chief-Prieſts and ſtiff-necked Jews made againſt Chriſt before <hi>Pilate,</hi> ſaying,<note n="*" place="margin">John 19.7.</note> 
               <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to die.</hi> But how little this prevail'd for their impunity with <hi>the Judge of the whole Earth,</hi> the continued ſeries of the ſeverity of his hand upon that deſpiſed and ſcattered People for many generations paſs'd, even unto this day, doth ſufficiently demonſtrate. Thoſe religious Men and Women that ſealed their Teſtimony with their Blood, and offered up their Bodies in the Flames, for the Name of their God, in the Reign of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> died by a Law. But were either their Tormentors thereby the more juſtified, or thoſe holy Martyrs the more juſtly condemned in the ſight of the juſt God?</p>
            <p>I have made this Digreſſion on this Subject, for the ſake of thoſe in whom (with pity to them I write it) that Unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Spirit of Perſecution, is yet alive, and ready to re-act over thoſe barbarous Cruelties upon thoſe, who never did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36621:6"/>them the leaſt harm, but are (as to them-wards) innocent Livers in the Land of their Nativity. And that I may not ſeem to impoſe my Sentiments in this matter, upon the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of any Men, otherwiſe than by reaſon, and not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether ever I may have the like opportunity (whilſt on this ſide the grave) to dear my Conſcience, on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; I ſhall take Liberty, fairly and calmly, in the Spirit of Meekneſs to debate this Point, with all thoſe, who either (through a fiery miſguided Zeal) are ready to call for Fire from Heaven, to conſume thoſe, whoſe Conſciences are not exactly of the ſame ſquare with theirs; or who (through want of true Judgment) may be of the Number of thoſe, of whom Chriſt foretold,<note n="*⁎*" place="margin">John 16.2.</note> who <hi>think they do God ſervice in killing thoſe,</hi> who worſhip him, not in the ſame way with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And I am not without hope, but that I may prevail with (ſome at leaſt of) thoſe, that are thus minded, to <hi>hear, conſider, learn,</hi> and <hi>forbear</hi> to ſtrive with their Maker, <hi>leſt haply</hi> (<note n="†" place="margin">Acts 5.35, 39.</note> as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> that prudent Doctor of Law cautio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Perſecutors of the Apoſtles in the Jewiſh Sanhedrim) <hi>they ſhould be found even to fight against God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That<note n="‖" place="margin">Fides non eſt cogenda.</note> Faith is not to be forced, is a Principle that hath been aſſerted and ſtrenuouſly maintained, for Scores of Years paſs'd, by many Proteſtant Pens, as a Bulwark againſt all Impoſition, by thoſe of the Romiſh Religion. And what was then thought, to be a reaſonable Defence of a Proteſtant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Papiſt, may now be as truly urg'd for the Defence of a Proteſtant againſt all Impoſition from his Fellow Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. No attempt ought to be made, to force Faith; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe indeed it cannot be forced. No man can by compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be wrought into a hearty Complyance with any Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, of the Truth of which his Underſtanding is not firſt fully convinc'd. The inward belief of Truth, was never the Product of Violence. Penalties and Priſons may produce Fear, and Fear beget an outward Conformity, to what the Heart doth not believe, which is but horrid Hypocriſie, and a Sin exceeding ſinful, in the Sight of that God,<note n="*⁎*" place="margin">Pſal. 51.6.</note> 
               <hi>who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Truth in the inward Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man can be dragoon'd, or tormented into a hearty embracing of any Religion, of the Truth of which he is not inwardly perſwaded. It is Illumination only (not Mulcts,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36621:6"/>and corporal Puniſhments) that can beget a change in Mens minds. Error is a Malady of the Underſtanding, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever would cure, muſt apply proper Remedies, and ſuch as can effectually reach the diſtemper'd part, which are not <hi>Afflictions,</hi> and <hi>Torments</hi> laid upon the Body, but Arguments joyn'd with gentle Admonitions, and wholſome Exhortations; theſe only can work true inward Convictions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when Chriſt Jeſus ſent forth his Meſſengers, for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of Nations into his Church, he did not furniſh them with weapons of force, and compulſion, but with power and inſtructions, to preach the Goſpel of Salvation, which joyn'd with the Example of their holy Lives, might prove prevalent for the making many (who were Enemies to it) become Members of his heavenly Kingdom. They that will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to make men Members of the Church of Chriſt, muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to the uſe of Chriſt's Methods only, for the effecting it. A Troop of malicious Informers, and Files of Muſqueteers, are improper Agents to reduce men from Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and bring them into, or conduct them on in the way, that leads to Heaven, and Eternal Happineſs. Would not that Chirurgion appear very ridiculous among men of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, who, when a Perſon ſought to him for the Cure of a Wound in his Head, ſhould (with the neglect of that part) apply only a Plaiſter to his Heel? As irregularly do they proceed, who attempt to remove Errour (or ſuppoſed Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) out of Men's minds, by Confiſcation of their Eſtates, Impriſonment of their Perſons, and the ruin of their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, whilſt their Underſtandings remain unilluminated, and their Judgments (which are the Seat of Errour) by the Power of Truth not rightly informed, and conſequently the inward Wound in their minds, left unhealed. Chriſt ſent forth his Apoſtles to <hi>invite,</hi> not to <hi>worry</hi> ſheep into his Fold; and to add to the Number of his Diſciples, not by outward Force and Compulſion, but by the inward Efficacy of ſound Doctrin, that might reach Men's underſtandings, and gentle Perſwaſives that might win upon their Affections.<note n="*⁎*" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>the Terrour of the Lord we do</hi> (not menace, but) <hi>perſwade men;</hi> and preſently after adds,<note n="†" place="margin">Ver. 20.</note> 
               <hi>We are Ambaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us; We pray you in Chriſt's ſtead, be ye reconciled to God.</hi> What ſoft
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36621:7"/>and alluring methods, doth the <hi>only wiſe</hi> and merciful God uſe, by his Meſſengers, to negotiate for Peace betwixt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and poor Mortals! The Ambaſſage, on which he ſends them, is not accompanied with Fire, and Sword, but with <hi>gentle intreaties;</hi> not with <hi>perſecution,</hi> but with Prayers. And why ſhould vain Man (filled with fiery Zeal) pretend to be wiſer than his Maker, in attempting, by other means, than he hath appointed, to reclaim thoſe that are ſuppoſed to err from the way of Truth? I ſhall cloſe what I have to ſay on this Subject, with the following particulars, which I heartily recommend to the ſerious, and impartial conſideration of all thoſe who are real lovers of, and ſearchers after Truth, for Truth's ſake.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Let it be conſidered, whether outward forc'd confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to any ſort of worſhip (not mixt with faith in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper) be a Sacrifice well-pleaſing unto God; ſince the Scripture is poſitive that<note n="*⁎*" place="margin">Heb. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>without faith its impoſſible to pleaſe</hi> him, and which is more, that<note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 14.23.</note> 
                  <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſin?</hi> And conſequently whether they, who, by Terrours, and Torments do force men to any external form of Worſhip, of the truth of which they are not inwardly perſwaded, do not thereby compel them to Sin, by offering up ſuch an obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Almighty God, which at the very time of ſuch their offering, they do not believe is acceptable to him, or that they are accepted for its ſake? and whether the Perſons that do ſo ſin, or they that forcibly provoke them thereunto, are to be adjudg'd the leaſt Offenders, I leave to be decided by the Judge of the whole Earth, who cannot err in Judgment.</item>
               <item>2. Whether they, who, with all imaginable Severities, have proſecuted thoſe, who only differ'd from them in their way of religious Worſhip (having the breach of no other Law to charge them with) have not manifeſtly violated that <hi>Royal</hi> Law of Chriſt Jeſus (to which all mankind ſtands obliged to conform) Viz.<note n="‖" place="margin">Matt. 7.12.</note> 
                  <hi>All things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye, even ſo, to them?</hi> And as a proof thereof, I earneſtly deſire them to lay their hands upon their hearts, and without prejudice and paſſion, in the cool of the day (reflecting upon the Cruelties they have exerciſed upon others) to put this Query to themſelves: Have we done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe our ſuffering Neighbours, as we would they ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36621:7"/>do unto us? Would we be content, that they (if furniſhed with outward authority) ſhould force, or endeavour to force us, to conform to that way of Worſhip, or embrace that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which in our conſciences we do not believe to be true? And, in caſe of our refuſal to comply (for conſcience ſake) ſhould we judge it Chriſtian dealing in them to mete back the ſame meaſure to us, which we formerly did mete to them, by caſting our perſons into Priſon, ſpoyling us of our Goods, and endeavouring the ruine of our Families? If men would deal honeſtly with their own hearts, it would not be difficult to conclude, what the anſwer would be.</item>
               <item>3. Nor is it leſs worthy duly to be conſidered, whether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or attempts to impoſe, upon Conſcience in things religious, be not a high, and manifeſt contradiction to the Spirit of Truth, ſpeaking by the mouth of the holy Apoſtle, who (debating of things pertaining to Conſcience) ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Let every man be fully perſwaded,</hi> or (as in the Margent of the Bible) <hi>fully aſſured in his own mind.</hi> A full inward perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, removes ſo much as the leaſt doubt of the truth of what a man doth embrace, or practiſe in the Worſhip of God. He that made man, neither requires, or expects from him blind obedience, that he ſhould ſerve him with his lips, or with bodily ſervice, until he be fully perſwaded in his mind, that his obedience is ſuch, with which he will be well-pleaſed. And what a vaſt difference there is betwixt forc'd Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, obtained by the imperious mandates of men, and full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward aſſurance of the truth of what they conform to, I leave to all the wiſe in heart to determine.</item>
               <item>4. And above all it's ſeriouſly to be minded, whether eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, as a Creature, ſtanding obliged to render an account of himſelf to God his Creatour, it be not agreeable to right reaſon, as well as to the Scriptures, that he ſhould manage the concerns of his own Soul (which relate unto ſalvation) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what he himſelf doth underſtand, and believe?</item>
            </list>
            <p>Upon this conſideration it was, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows no man to impoſe upon his Brother's conſcience, no, not in thoſe low concerns of <hi>meats,</hi> and obſervation of <hi>days,</hi> for, ſaith he,<note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>To his own Maſter he ſtandeth, or falleth,</hi> and preſently ſubjoyns, <hi>Every one of us</hi> (including himſelf among the reſt) <hi>ſhall give account of himſelf to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36621:8"/>
            <p> When Death <hi>(the King of Terrours)</hi> ſhall ſummon any man from off the Stage of this World, nothing is more certain, than that he muſt then die for himſelf. No man can, at that hour, die in his brother's ſtead, much leſs can he make up his Soul's account for him with Almighty God. If poor Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, when they come to lye upon their dying Beds, ſhould then call to thoſe, who had before forc'd (or endeavour'd to force) them, to conform to what they did not believe to be true, crying out, in the anguiſh of their hearts, and ſaying, Oh! now come and help us, we have no inward peace in our boſoms: Now ſhoot the bottomleſs gulf of Eternity for us, in our ſteads: We are ſhortly to appear before the great Tribunal of the ever-living God, to give an account of all our deeds done in theſe bodies. Now therefore ſtand by us, and for the eternal ſafety of our immortal Souls, make up a ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory account to him for us. What other returns could they then receive to their mournful cries, but this heart-breaking anſwer? <hi>(viz.)</hi> We can neither die for you, nor give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God for you; we now leave you to do both for your ſelves. What can be more unreaſonable, than that men ſhould by Pains and Penalties be violently driven to renounce their own Faith, and way of Worſhip, and conform to another's whileſt they <hi>live,</hi> and be bid to ſhift for themſelves when they come to <hi>die?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having for the reaſon before-mentioned made this digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I come now to reckon with my nameleſs Adverſaries, touching the Contents of their ſcoffing Libel. And in the firſt place, I cannot forbear telling you, that you make too bold with many Expreſſions uſed in the holy Scriptures, by an arrogant loading them with your unſavoury Scoffs. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ye thought your ſelves very witty in ſo doing: But you muſt know,<note n="*" place="margin">Jocare in Seriis, &amp; Judere cum Sanctis.</note> that to mingle <hi>Ieſts</hi> with things of a ſerious nature, and to ſport with things Sacred, hath ever been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded by men truly religious, as becoming none but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane lips. You charge the Serjeant, and his fellow Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didate with <hi>appearing for the cauſe of God, at the head of his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Animad.</hi> Well, and what then? if you would have men believe your own words to be true, that they were (as you ſay) the People of God, in the head of whom they did appear,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36621:8"/>how can you fix this upon them as a crime, or make it to redound in the leaſt to their diſhonour? I find, through the New Teſtament, thoſe comprehended under the denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People of God,<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 2.14. 1 Pet. 2.9, 10.</note> who have obtained mercy from him, found favour in his ſight, and are beloved by him, and therefore Emphatically ſtyled his <hi>peculiar People.</hi> And if you exclude your ſelves from the number of <hi>God's People</hi> (as by your mentioning them with ſcorn ye ſeem to do) one may, without breach of Charity, doubt, if not conclude, to what herd of Evil-doers you do belong.</p>
            <p>You add further, that their appearing <hi>adminiſters comfort, and ſatisfaction to all, who are the well-wiſhers of the peace of Zion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Animad.</hi> The Scriptures make frequent mention of <hi>mount Zion</hi> with great veneration, as being the place of God's wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, where he is ſaid by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 8.18. Iſa. 24.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> both <hi>to dwell,</hi> and <hi>to reign;</hi> and therefore not to be made the ſubject of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion, by the tongues of Scorners.</p>
            <p>Pray, Sirs, obſerve, you are both Categorical, and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal in your Poſition, then let me ask you, Are you well-wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or enemies, to the peace of <hi>Zion?</hi> If well-wiſhers, then their appearing (as before) doth adminiſter comfort and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction (among the reſt) to you alſo; for under the word <hi>all</hi> you muſt needs comprehend your ſelves.</p>
            <p>And why then do you quarrel at their appearing? If you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me, and ſay, that you are enemies to the peace of <hi>Zion,</hi> (which I am moſt inclin'd to believe) you do thereby at once proclaim both your ſin, and your ſhame, by profeſſing your ſelves enemies to that, which God loves, and all good men pray for.</p>
            <p>You proceed on in your Epiſtle, to belch out your unſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Scoffs, againſt other Expreſſions of the holy Scriptures, which ſpeak the great Love of God to poor Mortals, <hi>(viz.) The Choſen Ones, The Houſhold of Faith,</hi> and <hi>the Holy Ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Animad.</hi> To be choſen by an earthly Prince, to ſtand in his preſence, and to be admitted a Member of his Secret Council, is a favour highly eſtimable among the Sons of Men; but how infinitely doth the happineſs of thoſe Souls exceed that,<note n="‖" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.13.</note> who are <hi>choſen of God</hi> (as the Apoſtle words it) <hi>to ſalvation,</hi> to live lives of holineſs, to his praiſe, here, upon earth, and to live with him in the Kingdom of Glory, when Time ſhall be no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36621:9"/>more! And believe it, Sirs, if you that are now ſcorners of them, be not found at the laſt day among the number of God's Choſen Ones, you will find no admiſſion into Eternal Happineſs.</p>
            <p>And is it matter of deriſion to you, that a man ſhould be <hi>one</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>of the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> or as the ſame Apoſtle hath it,<note n="†" place="margin">Eph. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>of the Houſhold God?</hi> Conſider it well; if your ſelves are not <hi>of the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> you muſt be of the Houſhold of Infidels; and if not of the Houſhold of God, then, neceſſarily, of the Houſhold of the Ungodly. And what the certain, future Portion of each of thoſe ſhall be, is worthy your ſerious and timely conſideration, before the Sands of your brittle Glaſs of Life are all run out.</p>
            <p>As to the Scoff ye beſtow upon the <hi>Holy Ones;</hi> let me tell you, that ye do thereby expreſs your diſdain of that which is the moſt beautiful Badge of a true Chriſtian. I will chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſuppoſe, that you all wear the outward Livery of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion, and conſequently, are all pretenders to the Kingdom of Heaven. But you muſt know, unleſs ye be found clad with the clean Robe of Holineſs, (the preſent Object of your ſcorn) your certain doom will be, to be ſhut out thence, for<note n="‖" place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No unclean thing ſhall ever enter into his Kingdom. There are none but <hi>Holy Ones</hi> in Heaven, and I much doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that ſcoff at them here, would make ſuitable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to them there. Thoſe glorified Souls are perfectly holy, and their Work to eternity will be holy, ſounding out<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 19.1. Rev. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hallelujahs, Glory and Honour to the Lord their God.</hi> So that it remains with me as a doubt, if Scorners and Scoffers at Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs were thruſt into Heaven (their Natures not chang'd) whether either the Exerciſe, or the Company of that heavenly Hoſt, would be well-pleaſing to them.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſhall come attended<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 25.31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>with the holy Angels, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the Throne of his Glory</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 17.31.</note> 
               <hi>to judge the World in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> he will then divide <hi>all Nations, that ſhall appear before him,</hi> but into two ſorts,<note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 25.33.</note> 
               <hi>Sheep, and Goats,</hi> holy, and unholy, and if it ſhall not then be your Lot to be found among the number of the Sheep, (the Holy Ones) to whom he will<note n="*" place="margin">Ver. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> ſay, <hi>Come, ye bleſſed of my Father, receive the Kingdom prepared for you,</hi> that ſad and irreverſable Sentence will then be pronounced upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36621:9"/>you,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Depart from me, ye curſed, into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil, and his Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You proceed on, to acquaint your Reader with the ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who voted for the Serjeant, and his Fellow-Candidate, <hi>(viz.) Presbyterians, Independants, Anabaptiſts, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Animad.</hi> But why did you omit to make mention of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral hundreds of ſober Churchmen, who alſo (as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) voted for them? Doubtleſs ye mention'd theſe Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſeveral Sects, as matter of reflection upon the two Candidates. But your ſober and prudent Readers will be otherwiſe minded, when they ſhall duly conſider, that to be of (or to be called by the Name of) either of thoſe Sects, is no ſtain at all, upon any mens reputation, whileſt their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion is accompanied with a good Life. Could you have ſaid (and that truly) that few or none voted for them, but lewd and diſſolute perſons, Men of debauch'd Principles and Practices, men of vicious Converſations, Drunkards, Swearers, Unclean Perſons, Envions Men, Haters of God and Goodneſs, Perſecutors of their Neighbours for Conſcience-ſake, Men of Turbulent Spirits, always affecting Domination over others, never ſatisfied, but when they can have their Feet upon the Necks of their Fellow-Citizens, and the Whip in their hands to make<note n="†" place="margin">Pſalm. 129.3.</note> 
               <hi>long Furrows</hi> upon their Backs for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity. I ſay, could you truly have repreſented the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for the two Candidates, to the World, under theſe black Characters, it might have look'd (at leaſt) as ſome ground of doubt, whether they had not been men alike qualified. But your expoſing them only, as men of different Perſwaſions in matter of Worſhip, not fixing on them any of the evil Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications before-mentioned: inſtead of ſullying the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the two Candidates thereby, you have certainly (tho' againſt your wills) done them great honour.</p>
            <p>Beſides which, you have (tho' not deſignedly) publiſhed the Diſſenters to the World, to be Men that did expreſs a great deal of good nature, by voting, as they did: in that they laid aſide all inward animoſity, againſt thoſe from whom they Diſſent, and (waving all perſons, that were of any one of their particular, reſpective Perſwaſions) did unanimouſly joyn with many ſcores of their Fellow-Citizens, to chuſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36621:10"/>two Perſons of known good Reputation in the City, which are of the Communion of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> And did they in ſo doing, do that, which they had no right to do? Have you, Sirs, and any ſelect number of Citizens, a Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by <hi>Patent,</hi> to chuſe Repreſentatives for the City to ſit in Parliament, with the excluſion of all others? Had not theſe men of your indignation, <hi>Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> both Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and Civil, to loſe as well as you, and your domineering Aſſociates? And is it not then equal and reaſonable, that they ſhould pitch their choice on ſuch Men, whom they, in their judgment, thought moſt capable, and heartily ready, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them?</p>
            <p>You go on, and ſay, that the <hi>Diſſenters appeared at the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, both ſuch as were within the City, and near you, and from afar off, as if they had been ſummoned by the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Animad.</hi> Hear you, Sirs, it's poſſible I may not have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to have another reckoning with you, whileſt I live; therefore let me prevail with you, not to deſpiſe my counſel, if I adviſe you, That (how bold ſoever ye make with Men) you beware (I ſay, beware) of caſting your ſcoffing Squibs at the <hi>Spirit.</hi> I have not heard, nor do I believe, that any man pretended to be ſo ſummoned to appear at the Election. 'Twas doubtleſs love to their Civil and Religious Intreſt (not any particular Summons from Heaven) that prompted them to their appearance.</p>
            <p>But rather than not throw out the dregs of your Venom, againſt the Men of your diſpleaſure, you would not ſpare to upbraid them with appearing by the Spirit; hoping that it might paſs for a black Character upon them, in the judgment of your Society of Scorners. Whereas in truth you have in ſo doing only publiſhed your ſelves to be Men, both of unclean Hearts, and of polluted Lips. You may vaunt it, and brave it out among irreligious Men, (ſuch as your ſelves) hoping to be eſteemed witty, in deriding the Spirit, and Men for its ſake. But know, that <hi>the living God</hi> (with whom ye cannot contend, and proſper) whoſe Spirit it is,<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> will not be <hi>mock'd,</hi> but will ſeverely reckon with you, for this your Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Do you believe the holy Scriptures? (you give me great ground to doubt it, if I may judge of your Faith by your Works) If you do, Pray remember what the Author to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36621:10"/>the <hi>Hebrews</hi> hath left upon Record, who, having ſpoken of ſuch who had done <hi>deſpite unto the Spirit,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 10.29, 31.</note> preſently adds this word of terrour, as a future ſtanding caution to all, that ſhould do the like, ſaying, <hi>It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> And if that conſideration ſtop not the mouths of all ſcoffers at the Spirit, let them always carry in remembrance that dreadful Sentence pronounced by the Lip of Truth, ſaying,<note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 12.31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever ſpeaketh a word againſt the ſon of man, it ſhall be forgiven him, but whoſoever ſpeaketh againſt the Holy Ghoſt, it ſhall not be forgiven him, neither in this world, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the world to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am now come to account with you (my nameleſs Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries) touching my Crime, and my Puniſhment. You ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me, towards the cloſe of your nauſeous Libel, under the ſcoffing denominations of <hi>the Ancient, Pious, and Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</hi> Ancient I confeſs I am, Piety I love, and hope ſhall continue a lover of, to the end of my days; but of that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which (I know) you intend, I do pretend to have but a very ſmall ſhare; chuſing rather to be learned in that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin which Chriſt Jeſus taught his Diſciples, when he ſaid,<note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly.</hi> True Humility, and Self denial, I do eſteem of, infinitely beyond all the Learning, that's acquirable in any, or all, the Academies in the World. But wherein conſiſts my tranſgreſſion? Only in this, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>free-born Engliſhman,</hi> and a Freeman of the City of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol,</hi> I did preſume (without the leave of thoſe, who would be Rulers over Mens Conſciences, as well as their Civil Rights) to give my Vote for the Election of two Perſons (to ſit in Parliament) both whom I have known for many Years paſt to be (and do underſtand now they are) well eſteemed in the City, and of the Communion of the <hi>Church of England:</hi> and had they not been of that Communion, I ſhould not (for ſeveral Reaſons) have given my Voice for them. And now, before I proceed farther, I will nakedly declare, what conſideration prompted me to Vote at all, or as I did, having not appeared, but once before (that I do remember) on the like occaſion in all my life-time. It was not (God is my record) out of any, the leaſt, inward prejudice, againſt the two perſons, that were choſen, both whom I have known from their youth upwards, and do not remember, that ever
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36621:11"/>I had any depending difference or diſpute with either of them, or they with me.</p>
            <p>But, having underſtood, that (both before, and at the time of the Election) ſeveral Expreſſions were dropt by ſome in the City, which I doubted to be Symptoms of deſigned Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours (at leaſt) to reſcind and annul the late Act of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to Diſſenters: I thought my ſelf obliged, to manifeſt my ſober diſſent from thoſe, who declared themſelves to be ſpirited for Perſecution.</p>
            <p>And now, before I proceed farther, I deſire the conſiderate Reader to obſerve how hard the envy of my ranckerous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies was put to it, to find out an Arrow ſufficiently inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed, to ſhoot at me, which rather than they would miſs of, they were fain to look back, and ſearch for one that had lain ruſting in the Quiver, for near Forty Years paſt, by which they do implicitly, (though not deſignedly) tell the World, how inoffenſive my Converſation hath been in the City of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol,</hi> that, during ſo many Years paſt, their quick-ſighted Envy could meet with no wrong Steps I had made, nor juſtly accuſe me of any Publick Misbehaviour in the City, either towards the Government under which I have lived, or towards my Fellow-Citizens, with whom I have ſo long converſed, with which they might hope, to blacken, or ſully, my Reputation.</p>
            <p>My Offence is, that I did dare to give my Voice, at the Election, without Licenſe. My Puniſhment muſt be, (becauſe none more proper could be found) to have an Information exhibited againſt me, for what I ſpake Nine and thirty Years ago. A perſon doth a Lawful Act in the Year 1690. for which <hi>(jure vel injuria)</hi> right or wrong, he muſt be condemned: Why ſo? becauſe of words that were ſpoken in the Year 1651. Rare Juſtice! Admirable Ingenuity! Pray (Sirs) recollect your ſelves, and reflect upon your method of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding. Can you ſuppoſe, that any thinking and ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Readers will eſteem it any Fruit of your Piety, or Prudence, or will they not rather conclude it, to be the Fruit of your Burning Rage and Fury, to charge the Sayings, or Sentiments, of a Perſon, which were uttered and expreſſed ſo many Years paſs'd, thereby to puniſh him for a pretended Offence, now newly committed?</p>
            <p>I doubt not but there was both a <hi>Tertullus,</hi> and an <hi>Ananias,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36621:11"/>in the Conſult among the Contrivers, when this malicious Epiſtle was framed. Pray then let them both be ask'd, when a man is indicted as a Criminal, in any Court of Juſtice, and upon tryal is found not guilty, by his Jury, and conſequently is acquitted by the Judge, would it be adjudg'd a legal, or a righteous act in any men, that ſhould appeal to the Judge, and ſay, We deſire that ſentence of condemnation may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be paſs'd upon this perſon, for that (tho' we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd he hath done no evil, in doing that, for which he ſtood indicted, being the ſame that we our ſelves have done) yet we remember, that about forty years ago, this man was very he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodox in his opinion, touching the Government, that now is, both in Church and State. Would not ſuch a <hi>Tertullus,</hi> with all his quaint Oratory, be hiſs'd out of a Court of Juſtice, for ſuch his illegal and nonſenſical pleading?</p>
            <p>Deep Malice and Subtilty were in conjunction, when this fiery Meteor of an Epiſtle was brought forth, and the Sermon reprinted; touching both which, I now come to a more ſtrict reckoning with my Adverſaries, <hi>N. D. N. K. J. E. S. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Are you not Men of brazen foreheads, who durſt affront, and run upon that Act of <hi>Pardon, Indempnity,</hi> and <hi>Oblivion,</hi> which King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second ſo many years ſince granted, and publiſhed to all his Subjects,<note n="*" place="margin">12. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. ☜</note> which was given to this very <hi>intent, that no Crime whatſoever committed against him, or his Father, ſhould hereafter riſe up in judgment, or be brought in queſtion against any of his Subjects to the least endamagement of them, either in their Lives, Liberties, Eſtates, or to the prejudice of their Reputations, by any reproach, or term of diſtinction?</hi> Of what outragious Spirits have you then manifeſted your ſelves to be, that (rather than not be ſome way revenged upon a perſon, that never did you the leaſt wrong, and upon whom you can charge no pretended new crime, but my voting, as before) you would not ſtick to tear off that ſtamp of Amneſty, which the King had fix'd upon that healing Act, and thereby give the World to ſee, that Acts of King, and Parliament, ſtanding in your way, are no more than <hi>Sampſon's green Withs,</hi> whileſt you are in the execution of your malice, upon the men of your fierce anger?</p>
            <p>You do hereby alſo give demonſtration, what you would be at, had you but a Law to back you, when as you dare ſo openly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36621:12"/>to violate, and trample under foot, a Law made upon ſuch weighty reaſons, and for ſuch great ends, as that Act was.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your deſign, in reprinting the Sermon, muſt needs be to ſmuch me, and draw a black line of reproach over me, thereby to render me (if poſſible) odious in the ſight, and raiſe a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt me in the breaſts of all that ſhould read it. To which end, I have underſtood, your Emiſſaries have been very induſtriouſly active to diſperſe it abroad among thoſe that know me, both within, and without, the City, that ſo, as much as in you lies, ye might ſtab my Reputation in every corner. But, Sirs, are you ſure, that by this method, ye ſhall gain your point upon me, among any, but your own credulous Followers, who live more by implicit faith, than by any rule they find right by due inquiry? If any moderate ſtanders by ſhould ask you this queſtion, Are you certain, that <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> doth retain the ſame judgment now, touching all things mentioned in that Sermon, which he ſeemed to have of them, in the Year, One thouſand, ſix hundred, fifty, and one? If for anſwer, ye ſhould ſay, We know not, (for we never ask'd him): It anſwers our end, if we can but expoſe him, and repreſent him in the ſhape of ſome monſtrous Creature. For we have envious Proſelites enough, (as bad as our ſelves) who ſtand full fraited with a ſufficient ſtock of Malice, to reproach, and revile him. Would not theſe men of moderation reply upon you and ſay, This is a method of proceeding neither Chriſtian nor Ingenuous? For that you ſeem to manage him, not ſo much by the conduct of right reaſon, as revenge, becauſe he offended you, by his voting. And, in our judgments, you have not ſo much ſullied his reputation, by reprinting his Sermon, as you have raiſed it, by that worthy Character you now give of him, in your own <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> acknowledging [mark Reader] that he hath, <hi>for many years laſt paſt, ſequeſtred himſelf from the world, and concernments thereof, to a religious, and ſtrict life, within the compaſs of his own family.</hi> Than which we know not what more you could have ſaid, to proclaim him to the World, to be a good Chriſtian, a good Subject, and a good Citizen.</p>
            <p>And now (my nameleſs Adverſaries) to confirm the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony you have given to the World of my Chriſtian manner of life, <hi>For many years laſt paſt,</hi> in which you have (though unawares, I doubt) done me right; I am come to let you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36621:12"/>know, that you have (in reprinting that Sermon) levelled it at me, as your principal Dart, by a wrong aim, and ſo have miſs'd your mark, and are wholly miſtaken in the man. For that, with equal truth, and boldneſs, I tell you, I am not the ſame <hi>Thomas Speed,</hi> that I was Nine and thirty Years ago, not boaſtingly (but with inward praiſes to that God, that made me, and hath ſhewed me mercy) I ſpeak it, I am not the ſame, that then I was, but another man. Many things, that were then glorious in my eyes, are now with me of low eſteem, and others which I lightly eſteem'd, I do now highly prize. I once thought little ſtrains of wit, to be great ornaments; and to be able to charm the ears of the hearer, with the <hi>enticing words of man's wiſdom,</hi> to be a deſirable attainment. But now, I do really judge one Drachm of the true knowledge of God, in Chriſt Jeſus, infinitely to exceed in value, the higheſt degree of the wiſdom of man, by which the world<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.21.</note> never did (nor ever ſhall) <hi>know the true</hi> and <hi>living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may ſay, with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>When I was a Child, I underſtood as a Child, I thought as a Child,</hi> and therefore <hi>I ſpake as a Child.</hi> And while I was under theſe circumſtances, my youthful years were attended with an inward affectation of popular applauſe, and by it (doubtleſs) was prompted, to intermeddle with things that concern'd me not, and to give my Judgment of things I underſtood not. And what then? What can you infer thence, at this time of the day? You do manifeſtly enough intimate, by ſome Expreſſions in your Libel, what you deſign. Fain you would intitle the two Candidates, and thoſe that voted for them, to the Contents of that Sermon, in which they are no way concern'd, it being (if reprinted as ſpoken) not theirs, but mine. And it's probable, that many of the Voters were either in their childhood, or not born, when that Sermon was publiſh'd, unleſs you would by a new-found method of Logick argue thus: <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The ſame Judgment that <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> is of, the two Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates, and all that voted for them are of alſo.</item>
               <item>But <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> is in his Judgment for Government by a Common-wealth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36621:13"/>How is your <hi>Minor</hi> proved? Why thus;</item>
               <item>The ſame Judgment that <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> was of 39 Years ago, he is of now.</item>
               <item>But 39 Years ago, he ſpake much in favour of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by a Common-wealth.</item>
               <item>Therefore he is, in his Judgment, the ſame now.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Your <hi>Major</hi> being denied, as notoriouſly falſe, (as preſently ſhall be made appear) your whole Argument becomes a rope of Sand, and falls to the ground, as having in it, neither right reaſon, good ſenſe, or one Drachm of honeſty. I would not do you wrong, (as bad as you are) but if you would faſten any thing of reproach upon them, from what I either was in my judgment then, or now am, your Argument muſt run ſo: That you would (if poſſible) wound them, through my ſides, is manifeſt, by your inſinuating to the Reader, in your frothy Epiſtle, as if they had an expectation of <hi>a new-born Common-wealth,</hi> which is in truth no other than a new-born Chimaera of your own brains, begotten of the fiery vapours, that aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the boiling rage, that lodg'd in your own breaſts. It's out of all doubt, that the Candidates, and they that voted for them, at the time of the Election, no more thought of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by a Common-wealth, than you thought of confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Act of Liberty of Conſcience to the Diſſenters. As to my ſelf, I would have you, and your Complices (and indeed all men) know, that from the time that it pleaſed the God of my life, to direct my ſteps into the path of Peace, and to give me a meaſure of the knowledge of my Chriſtian duty, I have conſtantly judg'd it to be out of my Province, to concern my ſelf about the Choice, or the Change of outward Governments: eſteeming it to be my duty (not to diſpute, but) to be ſubject to (and live peaceably under) that Government, which his Providence, who rules in the Kingdoms of men, doth ſet over me. The higheſt expectation, that I have from any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, but that I may enjoy the liberty of my Conſcience, and paſs the remainder of my days, in the Land of my Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, in the peaceable exerciſe thereof, without moleſtation.</p>
            <p>I intend not hereby a liberty to Libertiniſm and Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: No, God forbid. The Nation doth too much abound with ſuch Pollutions already; and it would be the joy of all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36621:13"/>good men, to ſee them more ſeverely curb'd by Authority. Not a liberty to do my Neighbour any Civil injury; by no means. No man may pretend Conſcience to dampnifie his Neighbour, either in his Perſon, his Eſtate, or good Name. The Civil Law is ſet as a guard to preſerve theſe, and he that will preſume to violate it, juſtly ſuffers by the hand of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And if the Government I am under, ſhall deny me the liberty of my Worſhip, and ſhall cauſe me to ſuffer, on that ſcore: Although this be an evil in the Government, yet I am not therefore to plot, and contrive its diſturbance, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, to obtain my eaſe, and relief. I did ſome years paſt ſuffer, both by impriſonment, and otherwiſe, for no other cauſe, but the Quiet exerciſe of my Conſcience to God. But I did not therefore betake my ſelf to Plotting againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, for the procuring my liberty. No, no, I bleſs God, I always ſtood firm, in the practice of that Chriſtian Doctrin of Paſſive Obedience, and Non-reſiſtance, and hope ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end of my days. Nor am I fond of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by a Common-wealth, as you would maliciouſly ſuggeſt to your Reader. For in truth, ſo little am I knowing in the Politicks of Government, that if I were ask'd, I could not give account of the particular methods of Adminiſtration uſed in that form of Government. But ſince I came to any meaſure of maturity of underſtanding, I have with my ſelf, often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired the Prudence of our Anceſtors, who contrived the Frame of our ancient Engliſh Government. For, where there is a Pious Prince, a Noble Counſel of Peers, Noble, as well by the inward endowments of Vertue, as by Birth: A grave Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of prudent Patriots of their Country, lovers of God and Good Men; I ſay where theſe three meet in one, ſteering their Conduct, with a ſteady aim, at the glory of God, and the Peoples welfare, what Form of Government can be found more conducing to the outward happineſs of a Nation, than this?</p>
            <p>You would farther bug-bear your Readers, and beget them into a belief, that I am now an enemy, to the publick way of Worſhip, by reaſon of one Expreſſion drop'd in the Sermon.</p>
            <p>Touching which I ſhall give a plain, and candid Account of my ſelf, by informing you, and your Confederates, and all men elſe, that I hate no Man's way of Worſhip, nor any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36621:14"/>Worſhiper of God, who doth with an upright heart (according to the utmoſt of his Knowledge) offer up to him that Sacrifice, which he doth believe is moſt acceptable to him; ſuch his worſhiping being accompanied with a holy Life, and Converſation. I my ſelf was educated in the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal way of Worſhip, from my Childhood: And was a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Worſhiper in that way; and do believe that God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted my Sacrifice, becauſe, according to my then-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I offered it up with a ſincere heart. And although I am not now in the practice thereof (being convinc'd of a way more agreeable (in my judgment) to the practice of the Primitive Chriſtians mentioned in the holy Scriptures) yet I neither judge, nor condemn thoſe that are; who (being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly concern'd therein) do in Sincerity, and Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs worſhip God, according to what is made manifeſt to them, and do bring forth the Fruits of Love, and good Works in their Converſations in the World. It's not the Worſhip, but the Hypocriſie of thoſe Worſhipers, that I do condemn, who contradict their Prayers, by their Practices; who do in words often pray, they may be delivered from the Sin of Pride, and yet live in it; from vain Glory, and yet abound in it; from Hypocriſie, and yet openly manifeſt themſelves guilty of it. Are not you (my nameleſs Adverſaries) fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenters of the Publick Service? If you are I blame you not for it. But conſider, do you not there pray in theſe words, <hi>From Envy, Hatred, and Malice, good Lord, deliver <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s?</hi> The Prayer is good. But how far your Practice is remote from your Prayer, let your Works ſpeak. Can you think, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny underſtanding and unbyaſs'd Reader will believe that your Hearts were not fill'd with Envy, when you contrived, and framed that ſpightful Epiſtle? Could the moſt malicious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Mortals, (I had almoſt ſaid among Devils) expreſs greater Hatred, and Malice, than you have done againſt me, in reprinting a Sermon, which had lain buried in Oblivion, for almoſt forty Years paſt, hoping thereby to murther me in my Reputation, and I doubt not, but in my Life alſo, had it lain in your Power? And as a Demonſtration, that it was pure Malice in the very Abſtract, that prompted you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, ye, did it without the leaſt ſhadow of any juſt provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation given you on my part. Is this leſs than a mocking of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36621:14"/>Almighty God to pray with your Lips, that he would deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you from Malice, Hatred, and Envy, when as at the ſame time ye were ſtudiouſly contriving (with Hearts full fraited with them all) how to expreſs them againſt your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? It's far from me to condemn any ſincere Worſhiper, in the national way of Worſhip. I condemn only that which God condemns <hi>(Viz.)</hi> Deceit, and Hypocriſie; when Men <hi>draw</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 29.13. Matt. 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>near unto God with their mouths, and honour him with their lips, while their hearts are far from him:</hi> And cry out the Church, the Church (as they did of old,<note n="‖" place="margin">Jer. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord</hi>) and at the ſame time live vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lives, and are found in the Practice of Ungodlineſs, and Prophaneſs in their Converſations; and ſo make their Prayers, and outward performances, a Cloak to cover over their Iniquities. This is that, which the Spirit of God in the Scriptures of Truth doth condemn, and 'tis that only, which I do at this day judge and condemn alſo.</p>
            <p>True Religion conſiſts not in the Exerciſe of any outward form of Worſhip, but in an entire reſignation of the heart<note n="†" place="margin">Prov. 23.26.</note> to God, attended with a holy life. An unclean heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſpecious ſorm of outward worſhip, is no other than as a painted Sepulchre, which appears glorious, and ſplendid without, whilſt rottenneſs and corruption poſſeſſeth the inſide. I am not ſo narrow ſpirited, as to confine acceptance from Heaven, to any one outward way of worſhip in the world; but do believe with the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Acts 10.35.</note> that, <hi>in every Nation, he that feareth God, and worketh righteouſneſs, is accepted with him.</hi> And, for a cloſe of what I have to ſay, on this Subject, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this, as my Faith, that it's not outward Service, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sincerity of heart, that God (the ſearcher of all hearts) hath regard unto. And whoever hath that, for the compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Life, will not miſs of Peace with his Maker, which is a Jewel of a greater Value, than all the Treaſures of the whole Univerſe.</p>
            <p>Happy will that man be, who, when he ſhall come to lay his head upon his Death-Pillow, ſhall be able in Truth to make his appeal to Heaven, with good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Kings 20.3.</note> and ſay, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member now I beſeech thee, O Lord, how I have walked before thee, in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have</hi> (not only ſaid, not only Profeſs'd, but) <hi>done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36621:15"/>
            <p> And now, for a cloſe of what I have to ſay to you (my nameleſs Adverſaries) let me adviſe you to the ſtudy of Peace, and to forbear troubling an (otherwiſe) quiet City, by your unquiet Spirits which is evidently ſeen, by your ſtigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing your Fellow-Citizens, with Terms of diſtinction and reproach, and thereby ſowing the ſeeds of diſcord among Proteſtants, at this juncture of time, when Unity in affection is ſo neceſſary, and by all true Proteſtants ſo much deſired. Be content, that (having your own liberty of worſhip to the full) they that live quietly by you, may ſhare therein alſo. Be not uneaſie in your minds, becauſe your Neighbours have gotten a little eaſe. Shew your ſelves good Chriſtians, and good Citizens, by doing unto others as you would they ſhould do unto you. Strive not to be Lords Paramount over other Men's Conſciences, for you would not, that other men ſhould be Lords over yours. And remember always that Sovereignty over Conſcience is the alone Prerogative of Almighty God, ſo that whoever do ſeek for Dominion there, do but juſtle with their Maker.</p>
            <p>What more concerns my ſelf is to tell you, that I owe you yet one Chriſtian Duty, which is (not revenge, but) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs. And I do freely forgive you, all the Evil, that ye have done, or had, or now have in your hearts to do, to me: and do wiſh you true repentance, that ye may be forgiven of God alſo. Believe it (whatever ye may fancy to your ſelves) by what you have done in the management of this buſineſs you have not ſo much wounded me, as harm'd your ſelves. In ſhooting at me, ye have ſhot your Darts againſt a braſs Wall, my Innocency being my Breaſt-plate. Your reproaches I wear as an ornament, and your malice is, as the duſt under my Feet.</p>
            <p>And not knowing, whether ever I may have the like op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of making ſo publick an application to them as now, I ſhall cloſe all with a few words of advice to all my Fellow Citizens, in the City of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Be frequent and ſerious, in the meditating upon the end of your being brought forth into the World, which was to ſerve the Lord in Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by bring Glory to his Name; Sin diſhonours him. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36621:15"/>which let his fear bear rule in your hearts: and as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 16.8. Pſal. 119.11.</note> ſet him <hi>always before your eyes,</hi> and <hi>hide his word in your hearts, that you may not ſin against him.</hi> Take good heed to the Dictates of his Grace, and good Spirit, which do inwardly prompt you to Holineſs, and will teach you (if hearkened unto) as it did the holy men of old <hi>to deny ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly Lusts, and</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent world.</hi> Let your Converſations be ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with love towards God, and love towards your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Baniſh envy from out of your hearts, and out of your Houſes. Be not offended with your Neighbour, becauſe his Eye ſight is either clearer, or dimmer, than your own. Bear not evil will againſt him, becauſe his Faith in every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Squares not with yours. If (through Temptation) he happen to ſlip, and fall, to his own hurt, rejoyce not over him, nor lay violent hands upon him, becauſe he is fallen, but lend him the hand of love to help him up again;<note n="‖" place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves, leſt</hi> you alſo ſhould be <hi>tempted,</hi> and fall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You that are Parents of Children, it greatly behoves you to be unto them Patterns of Piety, Patterns of Humility, Moderation, Temperance, and of every other Vertue. That, as they grow in years, they may increaſe in Holineſs, and as they are yours, they may become alſo the Children of the moſt high God. Let your ſavoury Communication ſeaſon theirs; and the Light of your good Converſations direct their ſteps into the juſt man's path. Their beholding your good Works may ſtrongly provoke them to do the ſame.<note n="*" place="margin">Plus va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla quam praecepta.</note> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are much more cogent to Piety, or Prophaneſs than Precepts. The moſt wholſom Precepts contradicted, by the Example of the Givers, are but as Water ſpilt upon the Rock. Children (through the proneneſs of corrupt Nature to that which is evil) are eaſily brought over to vicious Practices. Of which we have too many notorious Inſtances, among thoſe that are but newly come out of their Infancy, who frequently grate many modeſt Ears (as they paſs the Streets) either with Oaths, or Obſcenity. What is it leſs, than cauſe of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, to hear ſuch, who (by reaſon of their tender Years) can but newly ſpeak plain Engliſh, can yet not only liſpe out, but accent, an Oath? And ſuch as are not come to ſo much underſtanding, as to offer up a ſenſibe Petition unto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36621:16"/>Heaven, can yet call to their Maker to damn them.</p>
            <p>I would not uncharitably judge, or condemn any Parents in particular, but whether it is not much to be doubted, that they that are of younger Years, have learn'd ſuch Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities from the Example of their Elders, I leave to every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent's ſerious conſideration. They that are Innocent in this matter I know will not take offence at what I ſay; And for thoſe, who, on Examination, find themſelves guilty; I heartily entreat them for God's, for their own, and for their Children's ſake, to amend and ſin no more in that kind.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To all young Perſons in the City, my hearty advice is, that you would<note n="†" place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Remember your Creator, in the days of your Youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when you ſhall ſay, we have no pleaſure in them.</hi> Let the time of your Youth be adorn'd with the Practice of Virtue, as with a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Garment. As you now begin to live, as Men, and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, live alſo to the Praiſe of him, that gave you Life, Breath, and Being. Conclude it to be more your Happineſs to be good, than great; and to be holy, than high in this World. Let me deſire you to have a conſtant regard to the guide of your Youth, the meaſure of God's holy Spirit, which he hath placed in your hearts, as a Witneſs for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and againſt that which is evil: Hearken to its rebukes, for it is the Friend of your Boſom. This is that, which reproves you in ſecret, for thoſe Evils, to which no Eye, nor no Ear was ever privy, beſides your own. This is that which doth accompany you to your Shops, to your Counting-Houſes, to your ſeveral Imployments, to your Beds, and will alſo to the Period of your Lives. It was this, that inwardly ſmote <hi>David,</hi> and made him confeſs himſelf guilty of Murther, and Adultery, in the matter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and <hi>Bath-Sheba</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Sam. 12.13.</note> . 'Twas this that kept <hi>Joſeph</hi> chaſt, by which he withſtood the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his unchaſt Miſtreſs. And although he might (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) have committed folly with her; with much ſecurity from puniſhment by his Maſter, and with worldly Advantage from his Miſtreſs; yet (hearkening to the Counſel of this his inward Guide,) he gave a repulſe to the Tempter, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhall I do this great Wickedneſs, and ſin againſt God?</hi> Some of the Ancient and Pious Philoſophers knew this, though by another Name, calling it their<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Syntereſis,</hi> which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36621:16"/>filled their Souls with a continual averſation, to that which was evil, and a proclivity to that which is good. Let this Syntereſis, which, according to the Scriptures, we call the Meaſure of<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 4.7.</note> God's Grace, his Holy<note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.7.</note> Spirit, the<note n="‖" place="margin">Joh. 1.9.</note> Light of Chriſt Jeſus in Man's Conſcience, Let this I ſay be your daily Monitor. Let it be in your Hearts as a flaming Sword, to ſtop you in the way to that which is evil, and as a continual prompter of you to all acts of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>Be diligent in ſearching the holy Scriptures. Beſtow your vacant hours, rather upon them, than upon Plays, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Interludes. And particularly let me recommend to you the frequent, and ſerious reading of the ſecond, third and fourth Chapters of the <hi>Proverbs of Solomon.</hi> That which beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>Timothy</hi>'s Childhood, will no leſs grace your Youthful Years. And that knowledge which was able <hi>to make him</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> can (if with honeſt and humble hearts, ye wait for Divine Inſtruction) do the ſame for you.</p>
            <p>Be conſtantly upon your watch, knowing that the Enemy of your Soul's peace is continually near you. Live ſo, as that Death may not ſurprize you at unawares. But that, if ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned in the flower of your Age, you may be able cheerfully to give up, and ſay, Lord, we are ready. And if you are ſpared until gray Hairs become your covering, ye may (reflecting upon your by-paſt Lives) lay down your hoary heads in peace.</p>
            <p>Remember, O remember, that the end of the juſt man's Race (only) is <hi>Peace</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Iſal. 37.37. Iſa. 26.7.</note> : which is not to be obtained, but by walking in the juſt man's path, that leads to it, which is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs.</hi> Let no man deceive you, nor deceive your own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souls, I intreat you.<note n="‖" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Such as you ſow,</hi> ſuch <hi>you ſhall</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>reap.</hi> If you ſow to the <hi>fleſh,</hi> to <hi>worldly pleaſures,</hi> and <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> ye ſhall reap to your ſelves <hi>ſorrow</hi> and anguiſh: But if ye ſow to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> to <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> ye ſhall reap the Fruits of <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> unſpeakable.</p>
            <p>The worſt of men, which hates a good man's life, will yet covet the<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 23.10.</note> good man's end. But let me cloſe my friendly Counſel to you with this great Truth, That, if you would die the <hi>righteous</hi> man's <hi>death,</hi> you muſt (indiſpenſably) live the <hi>righteous</hi> man's <hi>life,</hi> or you will aſſuredly deceive your own Souls.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36621:17"/>
            <p> Finally, When all Ranks and Orders of Men, Old and Young, High and Low, Magiſtrates and People, ſhall live in the faithful diſcharge of their Duty of Fear and Service towards God, and of true Love and Forgiveneſs one towards another: Then ſhall the City of <hi>Briſtol</hi> juſtly be ſtiled as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of old once was, <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Neh. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>holy City, the</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Pſal. 48.8.</note> 
               <hi>City of our God,</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>City of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, the faithful City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, that <hi>Holineſs to the Lord</hi> may be written upon her Gates; that Mercy and Truth may ever be found within her Walls, and Righteouſneſs and Peace within her Borders:<note n="†" place="margin">Amos 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>That Judgment may run down</hi> in her Streets, <hi>as Waters, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs as a Mighty Stream:</hi> That that doleful Lamentation, which Chriſt with Tears once took over languiſhing <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> may never be juſtly taken up, over the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> ſaying,<note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 23.37, 38.</note> 
               <hi>If thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things, which belong unto thy Peace! But now they are hid from thine eyes:</hi> That the bright Sun-ſhine of Heaven's Bounty, and Bleſſings, both Spiritual and Temporal, may never be eclips'd over her: That all her Inhabitants, from the leaſt to the greateſt, may know the Lord their Redeemer; And that they may fully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe things which do concern their Happineſs in this World, and their Eternal Happineſs in that Kingdom which ſhall never have an end, is the hearty and fervent Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Faithful Friend, and Fellow-Citizen,</hi> Thomas Speed.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
